Guide to the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series I. Secretary's Office
  - Subseries I.L: Publications
    - Sub-subseries I.L.2: Works not published by CEIP
      - Noble, G. Bernard-Report of the Committee on Vocational Opportunities in the field of International Law and Relations, 1941 (Box 90)
      - Norwood, Bernard (Box 90)
      - Nosek, Vladimir, 1927 (Box 90)
      - Ogden, M.O., 1940 (Box 90)
      - Ottolenghi, Constantino, 1940 (Box 90)
      - Pfaul, Albert
        - 1930-1932 (Box 90)
        - 1931-1935 1946-1947 (Box 91)
      - Phucas, Andrew B. (Box 91)
      - Pirenne-Histoire de Belgique, 1929 (Box 91)
      - Possony, Stefan T., 1946 (Box 91)
      - Predöhl, Andreas, 1941 (Box 91)
      - Prodinger, Karl (Box 91)
      - Ravignani, Emilo-a History of Argentina, 1941-1942 (Box 91)
      - Reed, Philip-Reciprocal Trade Program, 1947 (Box 91)
      - Regout, Robert Hubert Williem-The Doctrine of Just War from St. August ine to our own Times, 1941 (Box 91)
      - Reichel, Harry R., 1919 (Box 91)
      - Reiff, Henry-A Century of American Participation in International Administration, 1840-1940, 1944 (Box 91)
      - Richet, Charles-Histoire Universelle de Civilisations, 1926 (Box 91)
      - Ridgeway, George L.-What do reciprocal trade agreements mean to the wage earnerÀ (Box 91)
      - Rosendorff, G., 1935 (Box 91)
      - Sady, Emil J. Exploratory study of the administration of international bodies loacated in the Americas, 1941 (Box 91)
      - Salomon, Gotfried, 1942 (Box 91)
      - Sato, Naotake-The Problem of Population and Industrialization of Japan, 1936 (Box 91)
      - Saunders, Kenneth-textbook on Asia, 1929 (Box 91)
      - Schiffer, William-Repertoire de Questions de Droit International Soulevees devant les organes de la Societe des Nations, 1941 (Box 91)
      - Schonfeld, Bruno-The Birth of War in Mankkind, 1939 (Box 91)
      - Schueller, Richard. Austria, 1915 1945 (Box 91)
      - Second Panamerian Scientific Conference, Concerning the (Box 92)
      - Shibley, George, 1940 (Box 92)
      - Sigfried, Thorwald-Congress Can Cure, 1931 (Box 92)
      - Sister Mary Barbara-Here and Now, 1936 (Box 92)
      - Smith, Wilfred Cantwell-Modern Islam in India, 1947 (Box 92)
      - Strupp, Karl-Decision of German Courts on Cases Pertaining to International Law, 1937 (Box 92)
      - Tannenbaum, Frank, 1943 (Box 92)
      - Tate, Merze-The Movement for a Limitation of Armaments to 1907 1941 (Box 92)
      - Tomlinson, John D.-The International Control of Radio Communications, 1945 (Box 92)
      - Town Meeting-Periodical, 1942 (Box 92)
      - Trask, Katrina-Without the Walls & In the Vanguard, 1924 (Box 92)
      - United Nations, Concerning the (Box 92)
      - United States Trade Policy and European Recovery, 1948 (Box 92)
      - Valladao, Haroldo-Speech at First Centennial of the Brazillian Institute of Lawyers, 1943 (Box 92)
      - Van Zeeland, Paul-The creation of a center of international action (Box 92)
      - Vasconcelos, Jose-Mexico-United States relations (Box 92)
      - Vico-Scienza Nuova (M.H. Fisch translator), 1940 (Box 92)
      - Victoria-Relectiones de India (Box 92)
      - Wambaugh, Sarah-The Saar Plebiscite, 1938 (Box 92)
      - Ware, Norman J.-The History of Labor Interaction, 1937 (Box 92)
      - Waser, Hans, 1938 (Box 92)
      - West, Raynard-Conscience and Society, 1943 (Box 92)
      - William, Maurice-Sun Yat-Sen vs. Communism, 1950 (Box 92)
      - Wilson, Robert R.-International Law in American Treaties, 1943 (Box 92)
      - Winderlich, George M.-Der belgische Justizstreik, 1943 (Box 92)
      - Winterfeldt, Hans Von (Box 92)
      - World through Washington (Periodical, American University), 1944 (Box 92)
      - Wythe, George-Industry and Nationalism in Latin America (Box 92)
      - Yale, William, 1925 (Box 92)
  - Subseries I.M: Publicity and Press Releases, 1914-1946
    The publicity for the Carnegie Endowment was handled first by Edward Marshall and then by the Phoenix News Publicity Bureau. Newspaper and magazine articles about or relating to the Endowment's work were collected by the Remeike Newsclipping Service of New York. The Phoenix publicity service reports in these files list these articles.
    - Edward Marshall Syndicate, 1914-1919 (Box 92)
    - Phoenix News Publicity Bureau, Inc. (Box 93)
      - 1926-1946 (Box 93)
      - Publicity service reports, 1930-1945 (Box 93)
      - Public information service reports, 1931-1932 1936-1945 (Box 93)
      - Baldwin and Mermey, 1944-1946 (Box 93)
      - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 93)
  - Subseries I.N: Reports for Trustee Information
    (Green cover reports) (13 boxes)
    These usually confidential reports comprise correspondence, memoranda, clippings, and reports that were retyped for distribution to the trustees. Reports with no specific title or which contain several different items covering various issues are filed chronologically; reports with a named author or title are filed alphabetically. The dates listed are those on which the reports were sent to the Trustees. The "Reports received by the Division of Intercourse and Education" are usually compilations of several reports, and May contain Special Correspondent's reports. Otherwise, Special Correspondent reports are filed under the correspondent's name. See also III.B. Topical volumes. Reports of Special Correspondents and III.C.3 Representatives and Associated Personnel of the Eurpean Centre.
    - 91930-1936 (Box 93)
    - 1937-1938 (Box 94)
    - 1939-1940 (Box 95)
    - 1941-1942 May (Box 96)
    - 1942 June -1945 (Box 97)
    - American Ambassador at Rome. Report to Director of Division of Intercourse and Education, 1921 Jan 6 (Box 97)
    - Association of Macedonian Students at Paris, letter from, 1929 Nov 12 (Box 97)
    - Atkinson, Henry A. Conditions in India and China, 1929 Aug 15 (Box 97)
    - Babcock, Earle B. (Directeur-Adjoint of the European Centre), reports by, 1926 Sept 1, 1927 April 18 (Box 97)
    - Basadre, Dr. Jorge (Lima, Peru), 1932 June 11 (Box 97)
    - Belgrade, American Minister at. Personal letter to the President of the Endowment, 1929 Feb 20 (Box 97)
    - Bishop, William Warner (Librarian of the University of Michigan). Reports, 1929 Aug 30, 1932 July 22 (See also Vatican Library in this subseries.) (Box 97)
    - Briand, Aristide, article about, 1932 Mar 31 (Box 97)
    - Burke, Judge Thomas. Correspondence concerning his funeral, 1925 Dec 1925 (Box 97)
    - Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1925-1937
      - Statement upon his return from Europe, August 5, 1925 1925 15 Aug (Box 97)
      - Statement regarding the new work of the Endowment in Europe, 1926 Aug 23 (Box 97)
      - Letters to the Secretary of State, 1927 Oct 17,1928 Jan 7 (Box 97)
      - Statement, 1928 May 24 (Box 97)
      - Itinerary, 1931 June 3 (Box 97)
      - Letters and other materials received by, 1932 Feb 29 (Box 97)
      - Statements to the Press, July 15, 1935 1935 July 19 (Box 97)
      - Abstract of address delivered in London, July 15, 1936 Report to Trustees on return from Europe; Letter to the Times (London, July 7, 1936 1936 July 20 (Box 97)
      - Correspondence relative to statement published July 16, 1936 1936 July 23 (Box 97)
      - Newspaper articles by, 1937 July 28 (Box 97)
    - Capser, L.W. Reports on the erection and equipment of library at Belgrade, 1921 May 17, June 1, July 29, Oct 21 (Box 97)
    - Clark, John Bates. Letter sent to Director of Division of Intercourse and Education with letter to Clark by Baron Sakatani on American-Japanese relations, 1921 June 15 (Box 97)
    - Collins, William J. (Special Correspodent-London). Reports to Director of Division of Intercourse and Education
      - 1923 (Box 97)
      - 1924-1930 (Box 98)
    - Conference on Baltic Problems and the Danzig Corridor, report on, 1932 Feb 3 (Box 98)
    - Crawford, D.L. (President, University of Hawaii). Letter, 1928 Nov 2 (Box 98)
    - d'Estournelles de Constant, Baron. Reports to Director of Division of Intercourse and Education, 1922 Jan 4, Aug 1 (Box 98)
    - Davis, Malcolm
      - Regarding, 1932 April 30 (Box 98)
      - Reports from (as Representative of Endowment at Geneva Research Center), 1932 June 1 (Box 98)
    - Division of Intercourse and Education
      - Assistant to the Director of the Division of Intercourse and Education. Letter of August 12, 1935 to Director, 1935 Aug 23 (Box 98)
      - Documents relating to the work of, 1929 July 19 (Box 98)
      - Letters relating to the work of, 1929 April 4, May 8, June 19, July 12 (Box 98)
      - Letters sent to the Director from Mlle. M. Th. Peylade and M. Paul d'Estournelles de Constant re the death of Baron d'Estorunelles, 1924 June 15 (Box 98)
      - Personal letters sent at the request of the Director, 1925 Jan 15 (Box 98)
      - Reports received by
        - 1929-1932 (Box 98)
        - 1933-1934 (Box 99)
        - 1935-1937 (Box 100)
    - Dowling, Noel. Report on year spent in England as Director of American University Union, 1929 Oct 28 (Box 100)
    - Economic Conference, Geneva, November 15-19, 1926. Report on the Prepatory Committee by Arthur Bullard, 1927 Jan 15 (Box 100)
    - Economists' Reports, 1931 Nov 21 (Box 100)
    - Efremoff, Jean (Special Correspondent-Paris)
      - Memorandum on the necessity of examining the moral consequences of the war, 1923-Oct 22 (Box 100)
      - Reports on the situation in the U.S.S.R.
        - 1930-1931 (Box 100)
        - 1932-1933 (Box 101)
      - Mesures législatives du Gouvernement Soviétique publiées dans les Izvestia, 1931-1932 (Box 101)
    - European Centre (Centre Européen), reports and memoranda on the work of, 1927 1944 1945 (Box 101)
    - Ferguson, Milton J. (State Librarian of California). Report, 1928 Jan 28 (Box 101)
    - Foerster, Professor F.W. (Special Correspondent-Lucerne). Reports on the situation in Germany, 1923-1927 (Box 101)
    - Foreign Bondholders' Council, report re., 1933 Apr 21 (Box 101)
    - Geneva, reports on events in, 1926 Nov 15, 1932 Sept 20 (Box 101)
    - Gerlach, Hellmut von (Special Correspondent-Berlin). Reports on the situation in Germany
      - 1922 Aug-1924 May (Box 101)
      - 1924 June -1929 (Box 102)
    - Giretti, Edoardo (Special Correspondent-Italy). Reports on the situation in Italy, 1921-1926 July (Box 102)
    - Grants to near east colleges, letters re., 1931 Spet 11 (Box 102)
    - Grew, Joseph (American Ambassador to Turkey). Letter, April 14, 1930 1930 May 21 (Box 102)
    - Hazen, Professor Charles Downer. Report to Director of Division of Intercourse and Education from Strasbourg, France, January 15, 1921 1921 Feb 15 (Box 102)
    - Heuser, Frederick W. Report to Director of Division of Intercourse and Education, 1923 Feb 1 (Box 102)
    - Holman, Alfred
      - Report on Brazil, 1926 March4 (Box 102)
      - Reports to President of the Endowment, 1926 April -May (Box 102)
    - Hudson, Manley O. Reports to President of the Endowment, 1926 Aug 30 (Box 102)
    - Hungary, report on economic situation of, 1931 Dec 17 (Box 102)
    - Interamerican Division, Director of. Report to Director of Division of Intercourse and Education, 1921 Jan 27 (Box 102)
    - International Chamber of Commerce
      - Joint committee with Carnegie Endowment
        - Preliminary report on survey of world economic and financial conditions, 1935 Dec 14 (Box 102)
        - Documents relating to meetings held in Paris, June 25, 1936 1936 July 31 (Box 102)
      - Letter from President of, 1936 April 28 (Box 102)
    - International Conciliation, extract from the British Weekly re, 1931 Aug 25 (Box 102)
    - International Organization at Work. An address by Professor Geddes W. Rutherford of Iowa State College, 1926 Nov 27 (Box 102)
    - International Relations Clubs
      - Cutting from Birmingham, Alabama, "Age" re the, 1926 Aug 30 (Box 102)
      - Re speakers, 1932 June 8 (Box 102)
      - Report on work of, 1942 Jan 28 (Box 102)
    - Kahn Traveling Fellowship Holders' Reports to Secreatry of the Kahn Foundation
      - Beaty, J. O., 1927 Jan-August (Box 102)
      - McKenzie, R.F., 1925 Dec-1926 Aug (Box 102)
      - Van Ek, Jacob, 1929 Feb-Aug (Box 103)
      - Weld, William E., 1928 March-Nov (Box 103)
    - Lange, Christian L. (Special Correspondent-Geneva), 1921-1929 (Box 103)
    - Loomis, Francis B. (Box 103)
    - Report to Director of Division of Intercourse and Education, 1922 Nov 17 (Box 103)
    - Confidential letter written to the Director, 1925 Nov 16 (Box 103)
    - Manchuria, reports on, 1932 Jan 12, Feb 29 (Box 103)
    - Misciattelli, Piero (Box 103)
    - Report from Rome, 1929 Feb 20 (Box 103)
    - Letters from (with Butler's replies), 1935 Sept 6, Oct 8 (Box 103)
    - Correspondence with, 1936 July 24 (Box 103)
    - Mitrany, David (Box 103)
    - Letters from Germany to James T. Shotwell, 1925 June 1 (Box 103)
    - Reports made as Special Correspondent-London, 1927 March-1929 Feb (Box 103)
    - Miyaoka, Tsunejiro (Special Correspondent-Tokyo), 1921-1932 (Box 103)
    - Molyneaux, Peter, address by, 1933 March9 (Box 103)
    - Monetary Problem, letters acknowledging the, 1936 June 29 (Box 103)
    - Newspaper and journal articles, 1932 and March, 1936-1937 (Box 103)
    - Nippold, Otfried (Special Correspondent-Beaumarais bei Saarlouis (Saargebeit)), 1920-1925 (Box 104)
    - Nitti, Francesco. Report to Director of Division of Intercourse and Education, 1923 April 16 (Box 104)
    - Norlin, George, report from, 1933 April 1 (Box 104)
    - Pact of Paris, cables exchanged between Briand and Butler re. ratification of, 1929 July 30 (Box 104)
    - Penrose, Stephen B.L. Letter, 1928 Sept 29 (Box 104)
    - Permanent Court of International Justice, resolution re., and statement re. Reduction of Armaments, 1930 Dec 19 (Box 104)
    - Phillips, Clarence A. Report re. his lecture tour in Europe during summer 1931 1931 Oct 1 (Box 104)
    - Phoenix News Publicity Bureau. Report, 1928 May 28 (Box 104)
    - Pritchett, Henry S. (Box 104)
    - Reports to President, 1926 April 12, April 29 (Box 104)
    - Report concerning the situtation in the Near East, 1926 Nov 18 (Box 104)
    - Report on conference on Institute of Pacific Relations in Honolulu, 1927 1927 Nov 5 (Also includes letter by Alfred Holman}) (Box 104)
    - Robertson, David Allen. Report to Director of Division of Intercourse and Education, 1926 Feb 15 (Box 104)
    - Russia (Box 104)
    - Report on, 1925 Dec 15 (Box 104)
    - Business conditions in, 1931 Aug 7 (Box 104)
    - Sakatani, Baron Y. (Box 104)
    - Report from Tokyo, 1930 Feb 10 (Box 104)
    - Letter and Butler's reply, 1931 Sept 11 (Box 104)
    - Sforza, Count Carlo. Letters and articles re his visit, 1931 April 30 (Box 104)
    - Shotwell, James T. (Box 104)
    - Report to Director of Division of Economics and History, 1921 Oct 4 (Box 104)
    - Report on the proposed Danubian Economic Conference, 1922 July 1 (Box 104)
    - Report on his visit to GerMay (by Reichgerichspräsident Prof. Dr. jur h.c. W. Simons of the Kuratorium of the Deutsche Hochschule für Politik of Berlin), 1927 May 24 (Box 104)
    - Reports, 1931 Nov 24 (Box 104)
    - Sino-Japanese Papers, 1932 March9 (Box 104)
    - Snowden, Philip (of London). Correspondence to and from, 1930 Feb 28 (Box 104)
    - South America (Box 104)
    - Three letters describing public opinion in, 1927 May 25 (Box 104)
    - Letters between Butler and Secreatry of State re. work of Endowment in, 1927 June 10 (Box 104)
    - Letters by Henry Kittredge Norton on, 1931 Oct 20 (Box 104)
    - Special Committee on Policy. Report, 1926 Nov 22 (Box 104)
    - Tarchiani, Alberto. Reports from Europe, 1941-1943 (Box 104)
    - Tibal, André. Report to Director of Division of Intercourse and Education, 1926 Feb 15 (Box 104)
    - Vatican Library. Reports (most by William Warner Bishop) on work at, 1927-1928 (Box 104)
    - Visiting Carnegie Professors of International Relations (Box 104)
    - Reports on, 1928 June 22, July 11 (Box 105)
    - Barrows, David P. Reports on his visits to Central and South America, 1928 May 7, Nov 2 (Box 105)
    - Bogert, Marston T. (Box 105)
    - Letter addressed to the Secretary of State by John Sterett Gittings in re Bogert (with letter of transmittal from Prentiss B. Gilbert), 1928 Jan 28 (Box 105)
    - Letters relating to Bogert and Barrows, 1928 March1 (Box 105)
    - Blakeslee, George H. Reports on visits to Japan, China, New Zealand, and Australia, 1928 March29, Sept 29 (Box 105)
    - Calhoun, George. Letter, 1928 Nov 20 (Box 105)
    - Garner, J.W. Report, 1929 Aug 15 (Box 105)
    - Monroe, Paul. Report, 1928 Sept 29 (Box 105)
    - Nakaseko, Rokuro. Report, 1929 Sept 12 (Box 105)
    - Russell, James E. Report on visit to Australia, 1928 May 7 (Box 105)
    - Also includes report on Blakeslee by Dr. Chamg, President of Kwang Hua University of Shanghai, China (Box 105)
    - Slusser, Herbert. Report, 1931 Aug 25 (Box 105)
    - Suzzallo, Henry. Reports on visits to Austria, Poland, Hunhary, Romania, Bulgaria, Yugoslavia, Turkey, and Italy, 1928 May 7, 1929 March6 (Box 105)
    - Visits (Box 105)
    - American Editorial Writers European Visit. Report by Lawton B. Evans, 1927 Nov 15 (Box 105)
    - British Journalists who visited the U.S. in 1928 as guests of the Endowment, letters from, 1929 Feb 19 (Box 105)
    - von Pflügl. Letter from Vienna, 1930 Aug 13 (Box 105)
    - Wilson, Florence. Letter upon her trip to the Orient, 1930 Feb 28 (Box 105)
  - Subseries I.O: Second Pan American Scientific Congress
    - Two volumes. (Volume 510-511)
- Series II: Division of Economics of History, 1910-1930
  (31 vols)
  The Division of Economics and History was established at a conference in Berne, Switzerland called by the Endowment in August 1911. John Bates Clark, the Division's first director, led the conference. The participants considered the best methods "to promote a thorough and scientific investigation of the causes and the results of war." The conference resulted in a plan of investigation and an extensive list of topics for study. The aim of the studies was to reveal direct and indirect consequences of warfare.
  The Berne participants, plus two additional members, formed a Committee of Research, the function of which was to select authors, to consult with these writers during the research and writing process, to read completed manuscripts, and to recommend worthy studies to the Endowment for publication. After the outbreak of World War I, the Division was forced to alter its program. The Division commissioned a series of studies dealing with topics of immediate importance in connection with the war.
  In 1919 James Shotwell became General Editor of the proposed Economic and Social History of the World War. The Committee of Research was dissolved in September 1919 and was replaced by national Editorial Committees. In 1924 Shotwell was appointed Director of the Division. Soon after, the Economic and Social History of the World War series was brought to a conclusion, comprising about 150 volumes, and the Division shifted its focus from the study of war to the study of peace. During the second half of the 1920s the Division's publications included a series on the Paris Peace Conference, studies on Canadian-American relation (conferences on which the Division also organized), and several monographs on the contribution of economic competition to political conflict. (Source: Carnegie Endowment for International Peace: Summary of Organization and Work (Washington DC: CEIP, 1941), pp. 46-51.)
  Files relating the Division's collaboration with other organizations and participation in specific projects can be found in Series VI and VII. Copies of some of the Division's publications can be found in Series VIII.
  This series is indexed. (Indices are available in RBML.
  Electronic versions of the indices are in preparation.)
  Series II. is organized into the following subseries:
  A. General correspondence
  B. Economic and Social History of the World War
  - Subseries II.A: General Correspondence, 1910-1922
    (20 vols)
    - 1910-1911 (Volume 3)
      (Disbound and housed in archival box)
    - 1912 (Vol 4 (1-620) (Volume 4-5)
    - 1913 (Volume 6-7)
    - 1914 (Volume 8-9)
    - 1915 (Volume 10-11)
    - 1916 (Volume 12-13)
    - 1917 (Volume 14)
    - 1918 (Volume 15-16)
    - 1919 (Volume 17-18)
    - 1920 (Volume 19-20)
    - 1921 (Volume 21)
    - 1922 (Volume 22)
  - Subseries II.B: Economic and Social History of the World War, 1921-1930
    ( (11 vols)
    - 1921 (Volume 23)
    - 1922 (Volume 24-25)
    - 26-271923 (Volume Vol)
    - 1924 (Volume 28)
    - 1925 (Volume 29)
    - 1926 (Volume 30)
    - 1927 (Volume 31)
    - 1928 (Volume 32)
    - 1929-1930 (Volume 33)
- Series III: Division of Intercourse and Education
  (82 boxes, 218 volumes)
  The Division of Intercourse and Education was established on March9, 1911 in order to: (1) diffuse information and educate public opinion regarding the causes, natures, and effects of war, and means for its prevention and avoidance; (2) cultivate friendly feelings between the inhabitants of different countries and increase their knowledge and understanding of each other; and (3) maintain, promote and assist such establishments, organizations, associations, and agencies that are useful in the accomplishment of the purposes of the corporation.
  The original intention was to carry out as much of the work of the Division as possible through organizations already in existence or established for particular purposes. To this end, the Endowment entirely supported the American Association for International Conciliation from 1910 until 1924 when it was dissolved and its activities taken up by the Division. The Division made other substantial subventions (grants) to the American Peace Society, the Bureau International Permanent de la Paix at Berne, l'Office Central des Associations Internationales at Brussels, and various periodicals in the international field.
  After World War I, the Division made several grants toward reconstruction efforts in Europe, including the restorations of the library of the Royal University of Belgrade, the municipal library at Reims, the library of the University of Louvain, and the official buildings of the Commune of Fargniers in the Department of Aisne. Early in the post-war period, however, the Trustees decided to apply all of the Endowment's resources to its own program of work. The Division's grant-making activities were gradually reduced and eventually discontinued.
  To inform public opinion and promote international understanding, the Division published and distributed literature, cooperated with libraries and educational institutions in many countries, worked with students, conducted a program of adult education, collaborated in the organization of international conferences, and sponsored the international visits of statesmen and professors.
  Specifically, the Division published the monthly International Conciliation; collaborated with the Vatican Library in cataloging its manuscripts, incunabula, and printed books; established International Mind Alcoves in public libraries in small communities throughout the United States; and sponsored International Relations Clubs of students throughout the world to which it sent books and pamphlets to incite and inform discussion. (For files on these projects and others see VII. Projects.
  The Division maintained offices in Paris (the European Centre, see Series III.C. and the CEIP European Centre Records held in RBML for more) and London (see III.D.) (Source: Carnegie Endowment for International Peace: Summary of Organization and Work. Washington DC: CEIP, 1941 pp18-28.)